window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Operating_System - Memory_Management — Slot 7 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Memory_Management — Slot 7",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>A processor uses 2-level page tables for virtual to physical address translation. Page tables for both levels are stored in the main memory. Virtual and physical addresses are both 32 bits wide. The memory is byte addressable. For virtual to physical address translation, the 10 most significant bits of the virtual address are used as index into the first level page table while the next 10 bits are used as index into the second level page table. The 12 least significant bits of the virtual address are used as offset within the page. Assume that the page table entries in both levels of page tables are 4 bytes wide. Further, the processor has a translation look-aside buffer (TLB), with a hit rate of 96%. The TLB caches recently used virtual page numbers and the corresponding physical page numbers. The processor also has a physically addressed cache with a hit rate of 90%. Main memory access time is 10 ns, cache access time is 1 ns, and TLB access time is also 1 ns. <br><br>Assuming that no page faults occur, the average time taken to access a virtual address is approximately (to the nearest 0.5 ns) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1.5 ns</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2 ns</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3 ns</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>4 ns</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>4 ns</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/788/gate2003-78#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>In a system with 32 bit virtual addresses and 1 KB page size, use of one-level\npage tables for virtual to physical address translation is not practical because of <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>the large amount of internal fragmentation</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>the large amount of external fragmentation</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>the large memory overhead in maintaining page tables</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>the large computation overhead in the translation process</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>the large memory overhead in maintaining page tables</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/916/gate2003-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The optimal page replacement algorithm will select the page that <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2002)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Has not been used for the longest time in the past.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Will not be used for the longest time in the future.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Has been used least number of times.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Has been used most number of times</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Will not be used for the longest time in the future.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/828/gate2002-1-23#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Suppose the time to service a page fault is on the average 10 milliseconds, while a memory access takes 1 microsecond. Then a 99.99% hit ratio results in average memory access time of <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1.9999 milliseconds</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1 millisecond</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>9.999 microseconds</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1.9999 microseconds</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>1.9999 microseconds</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/669/gate2000-2-22\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is/are advantage(s) of virtual memory? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Faster access to memory on an average.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Processes can be given protected address spaces.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Linker can assign addresses independent of where the program will be loaded in physical memory.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Program larger than the physical memory size can be run.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Processes can be given protected address spaces.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1489/gate1999-2-11\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>A multi-user, multi-processing operating system cannot be implemented on hardware that does not support <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Address translation</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>DMA for disk transfer</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>At least two modes of CPU execution (privileged and non-privileged)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Demand paging</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Address translation</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1488/gate1999-2-10\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Listed below are some operating system abstractions (in the left column) and the hardware components (in the right column)<br>\\(\\small \\begin{array}{cl|cl}\\hline \\text{(A)}&amp; \\text{Thread} &amp; \\text{1.}&amp; \\text{Interrupt} \\\\\\hline \\text{(B)}&amp; \\text{Virtual address space} &amp; \\text{2.}&amp; \\text{Memory} \\\\\\hline \\text{(C)} &amp;\\text{File system} &amp; \\text{3.} &amp;\\text{CPU} \\\\\\hline \\text{(D)} &amp;\\text{Signal} &amp; \\text{4.}&amp; \\text{Disk} \\\\\\hline \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(A) - 2 (B) - 4 (C) - 3 (D) - 1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(A) - 1 (B) - 2 (C) - 3 (D) - 4</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(A) - 3 (B) - 2 (C) - 4 (D) - 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(A) - 4 (B) - 1 (C) - 2 (D) - 3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>(A) - 3 (B) - 2 (C) - 4 (D) - 1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1462/gate1999-1-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>If an instruction takes \\(i\\) microseconds and a page fault takes an additional \\(j\\) microseconds, the effective instruction time if on the average a page fault occurs every \\(k\\) instruction is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(i + \\dfrac{j}{k}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(i +(j\\times k)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\dfrac{i+j}{k}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(({i+j})\\times {k}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(i + \\dfrac{j}{k}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1691/gate1998-2-18-ugcnet-june2012-iii-48\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Dirty bit for a page in a page table <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>helps avoid unnecessary writes on a paging device</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>helps maintain LRU information</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>allows only read on a page</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>helps avoid unnecessary writes on a paging device</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2241/gate1997-3-10-isro2008-57-isro2015-64\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Thrashing <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>reduces page I/O</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>decreases the degree of multiprogramming</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>implies excessive page I/O</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>improve the system performance</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>implies excessive page I/O</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2240/gate1997-3-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Locality of reference implies that the page reference being made by a process <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>will always be to the page used in the previous page reference</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>is likely to be to one of the pages used in the last few page references</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>will always be to one of the pages existing in memory</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>will always lead to a page fault</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>is likely to be to one of the pages used in the last few page references</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2236/gate1997-3-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>A 1000 Kbyte memory is managed using variable partitions but no compaction. It currently has two partitions of sizes 200 Kbyte and 260 Kbyte respectively. The smallest allocation request in Kbyte that could be denied is for <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>151</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>181</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>231</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>541</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>181</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2747/gate1996-2-18\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>In a virtual memory system the address space specified by the address lines of the CPU must be _____ than the physical memory size and ____ than the secondary storage size. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>smaller, smaller</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>smaller, larger</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>larger, smaller</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>larger, larger</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>larger, smaller</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2628/gate1995-2-16\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>The address sequence generated by tracing a particular program executing in a pure demand based paging system with 100 records per page with 1 free main memory frame is recorded as follows. What is the number of page faults?<br>\n0100, 0200, 0430, 0499, 0510, 0530, 0560, 0120, 0220, 0240, 0260, 0320, 0370 <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>13</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>8</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>7</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2619/gate1995-2-7\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following page replacement algorithms suffers from Belady's anamoly? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Optimal replacement</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>LRU</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>FIFO</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Both (A) and (C)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>FIFO</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2595/gate1995-1-8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
